welcome back to am Northwest if you love
shopping garage sales our first guest
has tips to make your next outing easier
and more productive we welcome back
antique appraiser Gary Gerber great to
see you thanks for having me back um yeah
now is the season I see people out I
see the signs it's getting exciting so
let's talk about your number one tip
which is to bring something called a loop
or a magnifier yeah if you're if you're
going to be things you need to bring
with you on you're going to you want a
loop now this is I brought my giant one
for television here so we can see it
better sure you see it better but you can
oops you can get small ones to sit in
your pocket like this so you can take a
piece of jewelry and you can look at it
and see how it's marked you can look at
a piece of art is it a print is it a
painting and that sort of thing of what it
really get eyes as you get
older they get more more
important that's so true but then you
can see if it says 14 karat right 14 18
karat or whatever right and then
another thing you want along while we're
talking about the gold is you want a
magnet I got these off e Amazon but the
real strong magnet and then you want to
test it real quickly with your magnet
because for gold is not magnetic so you
got your pieces here that are all gold
and then this is marked 14 karat
and so gold is not magnetic
Gold's not magnetic and so one of the
reasons you would like it's good to if
you're going to be doing jewelry and
digging through the jewelry of course the
thing is if you don't have it and these
were all $3 a piece buy them all even
the even the other one because if you
didn't know if you didn't have a magnet I
would have paid three bucks because it
said it and then you're going to get
zoned every now and then but you know
that happens little bit money let's start
at the beginning so let's say you want
you're going to you and a friend are
going to go out and go uh garage sailing
right your first suggestion first thing
you do is figure out where you're going
and and the people who are The Weekend
Warriors who go every week have a plan
and so they'll look at there's three
basically three there's more than that
but three main websites to find the
estate sales which everything in the
house is for sale yeah you think those are
the best well you get the whole house
so if you're looking for tools if you're
looking for Toys if you're looking for
vintage clothes they're going to have
everything in the house for sale garage
sale they're getting rid of the stuff
they don't want right so you can
still find good things um estat salf
finder.com
estatesales.net domcom and estatesales.org
are three main websites that the
dealers uh will put the the estat sale
people will put their ads on with photos
so you can kind of see hey this looks
like a sale I'd like to attend yeah I'm
going to start there and make yourself
a route so you know where you're going
and you're not trying to figure it out
in your car okay I have another friend
who does it a whole different way he
lives in Vancouver and he lives near
mcgilvery Boulevard Y and he starts at
1 in all summer long they're all over
that neighborhood his middle class NE
and he starts at 1 end and goes to to the
other and spends his whole day and he
just he just filters out really great
stuff out of wow and so um so you might
do that you have a certain neighborhood
that you keep farming over and over again
and you get to know well either way is
fine but know where you're going and
don't be sitting in the car trying to
figure it out okay and then you say
just bring one friend only one friend um
it's a this is a ninja sport you want in
you want to find the good stuff and you
want to get
out and what how will that friend help
you with this ninja well the friend can
help you with navigation okay your
friend can help you if you buy a piece of
furniture pack it to the car got your
friend and you can can can can share the
joy of finding a great deal together and
having much and it's and it's a f but
if you bring four or five friends there's
always going to be Aunt Tilly who's
stuck in that box of Rags looking for
something good and you're ready to move on
you are so right oh my gosh you're so
right okay so you also say to get there
early if you can yeah the uh you want
to start early in the day cuz you know
everything's there for sale right
you're you are working with the Weekend
Warriors who are out and they they
have their eBay stores or their Etsy or
whatever they do to resell yeah so that's
who the early ones you're competing
with but don't panic if you're not the
first one in there the old saying goes
that the early bird gets the worm but
it's the second mouse that gets the cheese
oh so I didn't hear that okay got
it and so there's always good things
to find and and later in a sale you also
end up with later in the sale with the
the the people more anxious just to barter
at the beginning they're going to try
and get their prices at the end they want
that stuff out of the garage they want
it out of the house so they're going to
make you much better deals okay and then
you also suggest to have an idea of
what you're interested in especially for
estate sales when everything in the house
is for salees so if you're interested
in vintage clothes sewing things Fabrics
things like that you're going to head
up to the bedrooms if you are looking
for for quote unquote gu stuff tools
and and things like that you might head
to the basement or the garage sure have
an idea and then I like the idea of having
something you're kind of looking for
because it can be just overwhelming I
mean you look at everything and something
pops out that's obviously you buy it
but yeah got you have a great uh I think
it's an app that you use to kind of
figure out if if something is worth
something it is if an item is worth
something and this is something my dealer
friends are just irritated with me that
I'm showing everybody you want to bring
what we refer to as the
Oracle which is your
iPhone okay got it cuz you and look
things up and this is good for people who
are setting up a sale as well
okay so you go to Google um go
to Google The Google and then at the top
on the where the search bar there's a
little camera on the far side you want
to hit okay and so then we have our
little figurine here and I kind of like
it but they want $8 for it I don't know
if that's worth it so I take that frame
it hit the button yeah takes a picture
the Oracle thinking Oracle thinking yeah
and we're in this I don't know if the
works here in the studio you know what
it may not work in the studio that's a
good point it pulls up all of these
uh items and these range anywhere
from $35 to $100 so $8 is a good deal I
see you know and it can help you do that
and so um okay that's a great idea that's
a that's a tip and that's only going
to get better in 3 to Five Years it'll
put me out of business the AI cuz you can
you know figure it scan it just like
an old St track uh trike order when it
comes to money just bring cash I
think it's a good idea to have cash
most of the professional sales will take
cards but um cash is King cash gets you
in and out of there fairly quickly have
smaller bills don't bring $100 bills
because it can wipe out someone's change
immediately and so oh sure that makes
sense so bring bring some 20s and
have cash also bring uh with you a
box some boxes and wraps if you buy
an $8 Bird that's worth 40 bucks
you can wrap it up cuz most sales don't
have bags and stuff like so you can do
that so you want to make sure you're
prepared that you can take stuff away if
you buy a piece of furniture for example
a chest of drawers and you have to come
back for it you're going to Mark sold on
it take a picture of it take a p write
the address down I can't tell you how
many estate sales I've run where somebody
bought something and never came back CU
they forgot where we were at and take
one of the drawers with you oh that's
smart because then they can't sell it to
somebody else who comes along and says
they want more yeah or or in the fog of
war the soul time comes off and somebody
else sells it and you're out I so take
a drawer with you and then uh but go
back and get it I've also had this is
serious business oh I'm oh my goodness
okay uh and then bartering you say that
everyone really has a technique for
bartering everybody barters um and people
who are running it at the beginning don't
really want to barter yeah because you
know they should have a chance to get
what they feel it's worth but at the end
they really are interested in bartering
and the best way of doing it is to be
polite be can you take this watch or
what is your best that you could do me on
this really like it could I get a better
price the PE and and if you're going to
make an offer don't offer less than
half if you can't pay half then you then
just let it go yeah really good
tips Gary thank you so much